ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

SUMMARY

Program Manager and Data Scientist delivering \$1.54B with 8+ years of proven experience. Established and scaled enterprise—level Digital Transformations across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Delivered core engineering AI solutions for British Petroleum and enabled Data Science's 69% AI market share within BP US Onshore Upstream O&G. Produced \$500M+ via a patent—pending computational chemistry solution for INFICON's Semiconductor business.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Program Manager

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present

Denver, Colorado

- · Acquired 52% of Exploration & Development's AI/ML market and enabled the team's 69% AI/ML market share across the organization spearheading in-house AI development & Digital Transformation strategy.
- · Delivered 100% of the Q2/Q3 Agile Features in Data Science, Generative AI, and Machine Learning Engineering.
- · Architected key partnerships with the Subsurface Technology Team and the Head of Performance Optimization.
- · Orchestrated internal forums with Digital Transformation Leaders across Saudi Aramco, ADNOC, and the U.S. DOE.

Product Owner

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- · Realized \$4MM in annual cost reductions prioritizing developer resources to build and deploy ML Sand Flowback.
- · Coordinated stakeholder timelines and prioritized developer resources launching ML Drilling AFE Cost Prediction.
- · Productionalized Long-term Production Risk for Subsurface Technology's Reservoir Engineering via Streamlit.
- · Coordinated between BP and the US Department of Energy on integrating technology for produced water optimization.
- · Oversaw the Azure to AWS cloud migration for the Salt Water Disposal and Productivity Index Power BI reports.

Senior Data Scientist

British Petroleum (BP)

February 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- · Generated \$977MM for Permian with a \$700MM NPV well development plan and \$277MM Drilling & Completions cost reductions by productionalizing Techlog AI Lithofacies enabling well prospecting and fluid mobility assessments.
- · Delivered \$540MM NPV for Permian Reservoir Engineering deploying AI Completions Optimization in Streamlit.
- · Drove \$20MM NPV for Eagle Ford Reservoir Engineering launching ML Refracturing Production Forecasting.
- · Collaborated with Subsurface Technology to address Eagle Ford wellbore instability predicting \$60MM cost savings.
- · Interfaced with the Head of Performance Optimization on engineered completions estimating a 10% 20% uplift.

Data Scientist INFICON

June 2018 – February 2023 Syracuse, New York

- · Directed \$500M+ in forecasted annual cost reductions and provisioned Neural Processing Units to support patent—pending Automated Sensor Calibration advances directly on next—generation semiconductor sensor technologies.
- · Produced a 21% enhancement in Mass Spec signal fidelity and designed A/B Quality Control tests for all Mass Specs.
- · Achieved 50% coverage for chemical detection & monitoring systems executing A/B tests with simulated GC-MS data.
- · Achieved a 95% increase in density estimation accuracy creating the Bijective Neural Architecture via PyTorch.

Research Assistant

June 2017 – August 2017

 $Syracuse\ University \mid Data\ Lab$

Syracuse, New York

· Modeled social media engagement metrics, formulating repeated measures experiments, utilizing Scikit-learn and NLTK.

Technology Analyst

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

June 2016 – August 2016 Jersey City, New Jersey

· Developed project business cases alongside senior team members and deployed code to live internal JPMC applications.

Software Engineer

June 2015 – September 2015

Self-employed

 $Syracuse,\ New\ York$

· Engineered information retrieval systems as a subcontractor for **British Petroleum (BP)** and a **County Government**.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Syracuse University | Hosein Research Group

August 2014 - May 2015 Syracuse, New York

· Awarded the **Dean's Leadership Grant** supporting simulation studies quantifying energy loss across solar cell surfaces.

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors

USPTO Application 18/686,753

August 2023 Patent Pending

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

Neural Attention for Seismic Data Processing

BP Geophysics R&D Seminar

July 2024

Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity

INFICON Data Analytics Summit

November 2020

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Core Analysis Workshop

UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology

April 2024/December 2023

Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX

Havens Consulting

April 2023

Power BI — Reporting and Model Building

Havens Consulting

February 2023

HONORS & AWARDS

Graduate Merit Scholarship

Syracuse University

August 2017 – May 2018

Summa Cum Laude Syracuse University

The Warren Semon Prize

May 2017

May 2017

Syracuse University

Dean's Leadership Grant

Syracuse University

September 2014

Dean's List Syracuse University

August 2014 - May 2017

The Founders' Scholarship Syracuse University

August 2014 – May 2017

EDUCATION

Tools

Syracuse University

May 2018

Master of Science | Computer Science

Syracuse University

May 2017

Bachelor of Science | Computer Science

Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Business Strategy, Business Development, Stakeholder Management, Change Management, Agile, OKRs, CRISP-DM

Technical Artificial Intelligence, Deep Learning, Transfer Learning, Machine Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling,

Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Monte Carlo, Time Series, Statis-

tical Signal Processing, Data Collection, Data Preprocessing, Data Analysis, Data Wrangling, Data Mining

Amazon SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, R, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Pandas, SciPy, Statsmodels, NumPy,

NLTK, Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog, Atlassian Jira, Azure DevOps